Finding Aid for Letters, Documents, & Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- Letters, Documents, and Other Manuscripts, Duane Norman Diedrich Collection, 1595-2007
  - 1787 April 24. G. Dent Partially printed DS to Thomas Harwood [Commissioner of loans at Annapolis]; s.l., 1 page; Receipt for fourteen certificates worth for interest on a loan-office certificate from Harwood, continental loan officer from Maryland. Signed, "G. Dent for R. Alexander."
  - 1787 December 13. J[asper] Yeates ALS to Edward Hand; [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], 2 pages; Has been unable to get Hand's hard money, and his efforts with Mr. Delaey and Richard Peters were unfruitful as they left town in a hurry. "We this morning announced the Ratification of the federal Constitution at the Court House. The inclosed is the Order of Procession [not present] & thirteen Guns were fired in Memoriam." Comments on deliberations on "the 10 miles square for the Exclusive Jurisdiction of Congress," and ratifying "the System." See also J[asper] Yeates to William Hamilton, March 23, 1789.
  - 1788 November 1. Ezra Ripley ALS to George Thacher; Concord, [Massachusetts], 3 pages; Fondly reminiscences of their student days and celebrates their lasting friendship. "I rejoice to find, that, my friend, who is pleased to stile himself, the Hebrew, has not, upon being called to take a seat in the first Council of America, overlook his old friend Ezra, who still attends to the feeding his few sheep in the wilderness." Comments on settling disagreements, discovering truth, and his longstanding views on religion. "The influence of your words, reach ye millions of America, and generations yet unborn. Your feeling and benevolent heart now has scope."
  - 1789 February 12. Aaron Woolworth ALS to Levi Hart; Bridgehampton, [New York], 2 pages; Read of the death of Hart's wife in the newspaper and sends condolences. Comments on grief, sympathy, and religion.
  - 1789 March 23. J[asper] Yeates ALS to William Hamilton; Lancaster, [Pennsylvania], 2 pages [total]; Yeates writes in the same folio as a letter sent to him from William Maclay, dated March 13, 1789, concerning "the permanent residence of Congress." Maclay wants to "bring forward information from every part of Pennsylvania to throw light on this important subject," and is disturbed by having not heard from Lancaster. Maclay presses Yeates to send the requested information and to have Hamilton "furnish some Member of Congress with proposals... relating to the Terms on which he will give grounds for the public Buildings, and let out Lots for private Persons." Yeates expresses surprise at the letter and "The Propriety of being peculiarly active at this Period." Advises Hamilton to speak to Clymer and Fitzsimmons about his "Intentions & Dispositions" as well as to write to members of Congress. Has heard that Congress "will in all Probability settle at some Place between Delaware & Susquehannah." See also J[asper] Yeates ALS to Edward Hand, December 13, 1787.
  - 1789 July 10. Newburyport, [Massachusetts] Selectmen DS; Newburyport, [Massachusetts], 2 pages; "List of the In[n]holders & Retailers in the Town of Newburyport the last year." Affirm that the list corresponds with licensed innholders and retailers from the past year, "and to the best of our knowledge, the persons named therein, have maintain'd good rule and order in their respective houses and shops..." Signed by Thomas Thompson, Benjamin Balch, William G. Johnson, and Edward Rand.
  - 1789 September 15. Jesse Root ADS to Sheriff of Windham, Connecticut; Windham, [Connecticut], 1 page; Orders the Windham sheriff to summon Moses Spafford to appear in court at Norwich to answer a suit brought by Levi Huntington. Huntington accused Spafford of neglecting his promise to provide "a good Merchantable House Frame" in 1787. "...in raizing the same the Deft. by Negligence & deceipt and for want of Integrity & Deligence & Skill in his profession raized said House Frame with one End thereof Nine Inches lower than the other." Notes the costs incurred in fixing the mistakes. Docketed on the verso by the Windham sheriff September 16, 1789, asserting that he read the writ to the defendant. Includes a list of costs, continuations, and defaults through May 27, 1790.
  - 1789 October 7. Albert Gallatin ALS to Alexander Addison; Fayette County, [Pennsylvania], 4 pages; Offers his opinions on government and politics upon hearing Addison is participating in the Convention. Believes the [Pennsylvania] Constitution needs amending but that the assent of the citizens is necessary for "any alteration which without subverting the liberties of the people might gratify the wishes of that numerous & powerful body of Men who from the first establishment of our Constitution have been averse to it." Discusses splitting the Legislature into two houses and the difficulties in making them true checks to the other's power. Comments on the Bill of Rights and the limitations it imposes on the branches of government. Notes the dangers to changing the government so soon after implementing it. Sending resolutions he hopes will be adopted [not included]. [Original in to be Gold Star collection]
  - 1790 April 13 - 1803 September 6. Robert Cook Ms; [Pennsylvania], 15 pages; "A bill of Rates Carpenter and House-Joiner Work Settled and agreed on by the Subscribers, For the County of Franklin and Shippensburg." Lists charges for various jobs and names of the subscribes. Also includes several pages of accounts dated from 1795 to 1803, ranging from labor costs to the sale of meat and hay.
  - 1790 May 13. Cha[rle]s Nisbet ALS; Wilmington, [Delaware?], 1 page; Discusses financial issues related to Dickinson College at Carlisle, Pennsylvania. Trustees have procured 1000 pounds from the State Assembly but still have as much unpaid in subscriptions and overdue tuition. They have threatened to sue but Nisbet believes it will be fruitless.
  - [1791 May]. John Kemp ADS to Cyrus King; [New York City, New York], 2 pages; Cyrus King's ticket of admission into the Columbia College "Second Mathematical Class from May 1791 to May 1792." NOTE: John Kemp became professor of mathematics at Columbia in 1786. With: Cyrus King AN regarding the ticket of admission.
  - 1792 February 19. Ms; New Brunswick, [New Jersey], 10 pages; "Constitution of Library." Notes regarding the formation of a library company in New Brunswick. Considers election of office-holders and their duties, responsibilities and dues of subscribers and members, purchasing books and maintaining a catalog. Describes the types of books to be collected, the arrangement of the library, and the processing of checking out books. Details fines and rules. (Box 2)
  - 1792 July 12. Benj[amin] Oden ALS to George Sibbald; Woodyard, [Maryland], 2 pages; Has sent Sibbald's note to him to Hugh Roberts for collection. Sibbald may pay either in money or in wine, "such as good sherry, Lisbon or Madiera, all of good quality."
  - 1792 December 21. John Wilkins, Jr. ALS to Clement Biddle; Pittsburgh, [Pennsylvania], 2 pages; Informs Biddle that he has not received any pay records. Will be at Washington, Union Town, and Denniston's Mill in January to pay "the officers & soldiers of the six months State Militia." Has not received accounts of men who used their own arms, so he has paid them in full on application. Inquires about other payment matters, including for Col. Irvine and Major McCulley.
  - 1793 May 27. Richard Varick DS to Daniel Phenix; New York, [New York], 1 page; Orders for Phenix, Treasurer, to pay Abraham Van Gelder to light the public lamps using the "Lamp fund." Docketed on verso by Abraham Van Gelder, acknowledging receipt of payment.
  - 1793 June 12. Cha[rle]s Nisbet ALS to Alexander Tweedie; Carlisle, [Pennsylvania], 3 pages; Comments on the uncertainty of health, difficulties obtaining good servants, and affairs in Scotland. Describes the moral state of the United States, lamenting the decline in religiosity and its negative impact on servants' behavior. Notes shortages in coal and lumber, the impact of the Hessian Fly, and other agricultural details. Laments the public's attachment to the "French Mob" and notes efforts to support the French. Mentions military troubles with Native Americans in southern and middle states, Native American distrust of the U.S. government, and his fears that it will bring war with Great Britain. Notes Britain's ongoing presence in Detroit and Niagara, contrary to treaty agreements, and his belief that they use Native Americans to gain more lands. Comments on politics and elections: "Their leaders & public Men are such as may be expected from the characters of those who chuse them, noisly ignorant, assuming & impudent, but professed Flatterers of the People." Discusses relations with France, French immigrants, Irish unrest, and his worries about the outcomes of the war. Mentions the administrative and teaching difficulties at Dickinson College.
  - 1793 November 4. H[enry] Knox ALS to [Lucy Flucker] Knox; Falls of Schuylkill, [Pennsylvania], 3 pages; Comments on the good health of their daughter. Notes frequent communication and travelers to Philadelphia, with some catching ill, likely with yellow fever. The "sultry" weather makes "the work of purification" difficult. The President has rooms in Germantown and is expected to remain there until they are confident in Philadelphia's healthiness. Believes Congressmen will also assemble in Germantown. Hopes that "you and the rest of our dear little flock" will join him.
  - [1793]. Abington, Massachusetts, Inhabitants Doc.; Abington, [Massachusetts], 4 pages; Abington town meeting appointed Aaron Hobart and Jacob Dyer as a committee to draft instructions for Luke Buknall, "representative in the general Court of Massachusetts," to uphold the law against theatrical performances. Believes the effort to repeal the law is "unconstitutional inexpedient and absurd." Repeal of the law against theaters "will equally conclude in favor of drunkenness bribery fraud adultery robbery burglary murder and every species of irregular apetite." Argues that prohibition of vice is necessary and that it does not impinge on the constitution or bill of rights. "...it is your duty as a member of the legislature to difuse wisdom knowlege and virtue through the body of the people as necessary for the preservation of their liberties and privileges, and to encourage industry frugality and punctuality in their dealings." Underscores the theater's harm to the poor and young.
  - 1794 April 14. Doc. to Gardener; New London, [Connecticut], 2 pages; Account of costs owed by Gardener, listing amounts for repairing boats, pails, churns, washing and die tubs, and making oars. Also notes items purchased, such as lobster pots, hoops, and pails. Includes an account for materials for constructing a house, including "rum for ra[i]sing" the frame.
  - 1795 December 12. Theu[ni]s Dey Ms to Horanian Literary Society; New York, [New York], 6 pages; Opening argument for the Horanian Literary Society, titled "Is not Party Spirit disadvantageous to a Republican form of Government?" The speech details how a democratic society and the party spirit that accompanies it is antagonistic to the Republic. Underscores his allegiance to the Constitution rather than any political party. Blames party spirit for resistance to adopting the Constitution, the "insurrection in an Neighbouring State," possibly referring to the Whiskey Rebellion, and general factionalism. Dey refers to the Roman Republic and poses that it was party spirit that led to its downfall. He also references how "the evil of party spirit" is apparent in the Modern French Republic.
  - 1796 December 9. Moses Everett ALS to [H. Everett]; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 2 pages; Everett writes home describing his journey to Philadelphia. He mentions passing through Boston and New York. He describes his lodging and his activities, staying at the City Tavern and at Mrs. Skinner's boarding house in Philadelphia. "Judge Livermore of New Hampshire, Mr. Lyman of Springfield & several other Senators & representatives board at the same Place. Yesterday I was highly gratified on seeing the President [George Washington] & hearing his speech to both Houses of Congress."
  - 1796 December 18. Moses Everett ALS to [H. Everett]; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 2 pages; Everett describes being introduced to George and Martha Washington at their respective Levees. "The President receives the Gentlemen standing in a drawing room- those who are strangers are individually introduced to him, to whom he bows without taking them by the hand - a Circle is formed around him in which he walks & addresses himself to one & another just as it happens in the Way of common Conversations- the Gentlemen retire one after another or in small Parties after having tarried 10 or 15 minutes without the least formality..." Describes Martha Washington's Levee, noting social protocol and food: "Mrs. Washington Receives the Ladies & Gentlemen who attend In a capacious and elegant Drawing Room. When we entered she was seated with about 20 or thirty ladies placed on her right hand- seats were provided for the gentlemen by the side of them so as nearly to form a semicircle in the room- The President was there & took a seat beside the gentlemen or Ladies as it happened and conversed with individuals on common topics.."
  - 1797 January 1. M. Waring ALS to John Muir; s.l., 1 page; Waring notes the Lottery Company committee is willing to settle John Davidson's account, "in part in Prize Tickets & Cash."
  - 1797 April 2. N[oah] Webster ALS to [Barzillai] Hudson & [George] Goodwin; New York [City, New York], 1 page; Has given Isaac Beers an order for 500 selections. Spelling books are needed by the city. "While no other provision is made, you will find a ready market for all you can spare. It would be well to calculate on a considerable demand here." Comments on pricing and payments. "You run no risk in printing too many."
  - 1797 June 3. Rob[er]t Aitken ALS to John Nicholson; [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], 1 page; Robert Aiken, Philadelphia printer, notes his serious financial straits. Owes a $500 note to the U.S. Bank. "All my earnings, at least from what could be spared over Maintenance, has gone to pay balance of the Invoice of Books, Wood Merch'ts for Joins & boards of printing Office, Bricklayer &c so that I am pinched beyond measure, Unable to purchase a R[ea]m of paper to retail in my shop."
  - 1797 July. Henry Titcomb DS; Newburyport, [Massachusetts], 1 page; Payment of three months wages ($100.00) to Titcomb, schoolmaster, by the town of Newburyport.
  - 1797 August 3. John Erskine ALS to [Increase] Sumner; Lauriston, [Scotland], 1 page; Congratulates Sumner on his election as governor. Sending books for Sumner and his wife, including the second volume of his recently published Sketches and hints of Church History, in which are many "proofs, that even in this enlightened century the church of Rome has retained her absurd idolatries & superstitions, & her treacherous & persecuting spirit." Acknowledges several Catholic leaders that "were of liberal & tolerant principles." Sends books for "Mr. Hyslop's Colledge." "I know infidelity is making rapid progress every where, & therefore have sent for that colledge at different times, some of the best books in defence of Christianity, which are now become rare."
  - 1797 September 27. Union College Board of Trustees ALS to Robert Yates; Schenectady, [New York], 1 page; Need their treasurer to be authorized to receive "the donation of the Legislature" on behalf of Union College in order to pay the salary of a tutor, Mr. Yates. Enclosing a draught [not included] to be signed accordingly. Signed by D. Romey, John Glen, John B. Smith, John Yates, and Joseph C. Yates.
  - 1797 October 2. Rob[er]t Aitken ALS to John Nicholson; [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], 1 page; Has sent Nicholson's bill book that better meets his specifications. Hopes that Robert Morris (1734-1806) could pay him.
  - 1797 October 7. Staats [Long] Morris ALS to Lewis Morris; Fort McHenry, [Maryland], 2 pages; Calhoun will arrive tomorrow at Charleston. Mentions his desire to share "some West Indian preserves" with the Gibbes party. While he was on furlough, all but one man in the company caught ill. Yellow fever has been prevalent in the area but has not struck the garrison. Had his pocket picked again while on his journey from New York to Baltimore. Believes a Frenchman took it at Elton.
  - 1797 December 2. Rob[er]t Morris ALS to Israel Whelen; Hills, [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], 3 pages; Discusses problems with land he bought of Whelen and Miller, upon Israel Whelen's recommendation. Sold them to Europeans who sent agents to verify their quality and were shown the wrong lands. When they returned, they found that the real land "consist[ed] almost wholly of rocks and Stones, except some Part on the Slope of the Hill..." A portion of the land was also already claimed by others. Disappointed because the Europeans planned "to buy extensively of Pensylvania Lands and were recommending similar speculations to their Friends." Asks him what is to be done, "for these people expect redress both as to quantity & quality."
  - 1798 January 27. Rob[er]t Aitken ALS to John Nicholson; [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], 1 page; Attempting to set up a printing business, but Mr. Appele will not supply anything until he receives a stove and boards that he believes were wrongly taken. Is in need of "oil in Juggs, & pitchers ready for Mixing the black-- & some Coal."
  - 1798 May 14. And[re]w Hodge ALS to B. M. Mumford; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 2 pages; Comments on the figurehead Mr. Rush prepared for a ship, the Fair Lady. "...the head was to represent his Dulcenia--after the head engaged was painted & not til then, I observed she had a fancy Dress--the petticoat buttoned up to the Knee to I supposed your friend might be pleased in seeing & feeling (in due time) the handsome Leg--her delicacy would not wish it exposed to the Sight of every one." Had Rush prepare a new figurehead. "...this one has the picture of her Dearly Beloved at her Breast & a Letter from him in her hand." Comments on the need to paint and gild it.
  - 1798 May 30. Rob[er]t Aitken ALS to John Nicholson; [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], 1 page; Experiencing anxiety over "the present affliction." Mr. Vaughan has been promoting subscriptions to their publication, but he fears they will not raise enough money "to make any kind of beginning, as the funds for such a work I fear will be rather pinching, I do not speak of letter press, but a vast expence of copper & engraving &c."
  - 1798 June 21. Rob[er]t Aitken ALS to John Nicholson; [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], 1 page; Sending copies of printing business accounts for Nicholson and Robert Morris (1734-1806). The accounts relate to printing items for the Pennsylvania Land Company.
  - 1798 September 15. Charles Nisbet ALS; Carlisle, [Pennsylvania], 8 pages; Detailed discussion of various topics in natural and moral philosophy, especially regarding (and with untranslated quotations from): Erasmus' Colloquia Familiaria; Albertus Magnus; and Nostradamus. Compares Nostradamus quotes to historical events, particularly the French Revolution. Mentions "the Philadelphia fever," swarms of Hessian flies, political trouble between France and England, and American foreign relations with France. "The Strength of America at present seems to be the Command it has of the French West India Islands, by with-holding their Provisions, tho' I fear that our Government has not Strength enough to prevent the Sans Culot[t]es of the Soutthern States from supplying our Enemies in these Islands."
  - 1798 October 12. Samuel Eddy CyS; Providence, Rhode Island, 2 pages; "An Act for regulating the Fishery and removing Obstructions in Pawcatuck River." Signed by Samuel Eddy, Secretary, attesting to its veracity as a copy of the act passed in January 1798. Includes a paper seal of Rhode Island.
  - 1798 October 15. Arthur Fenner LS to Jonathan Trumbull; Providence, Rhode Island, 1 page; Remitting a copy of act on regulating fisheries in the Pawcatuck River, "in Conformity to one enacted by the Legislature of the State of Connecticut... of October A.D. 1785." Also sending a copy of "the Revision of the Laws of this State."
  - 1798 November 16. A[rthur] Fenner LS to Jonathan Trumbull; Providence, Rhode Island, 1 page; Remitting a copy of act on regulating fisheries in the Pawcatuck River.
  - 1799 January 21. John [Gottlieb Ernestus] Heckewelder ALS to Samuel Sitgreaves; Bethlehem, [Pennsylvania], 9 pages (total); Seeking reparations for losses sustained during the Revolution. Comments on his attempts to recover his losses and be granted land, partially to support a "Settlement for the benefit of the Christian Indians." Did not want certificates relating to his cause read in Congress, fearing it would reveal the extent of his espionage against the British during the Revolution and negatively impact missionary work among the Chippewas in Canada. Includes two enclosures: "Representation of Facts -- seting forth the suffrings and losses sustained by John Heckewelder during the late American war," (4 pp.) and "Inventory & Valuation of Property lost to John Heckewelder & family on Muskingum on being taken Captives by the Enemy Indians the 3d day of September 1781," (3 pp.) Includes commentary on Native American warriors during the Revolution, the sufferings of Christian Indians, his work among them, and losses sustained when he was taken captive in 1781.
  - 1799 April 15. H[enr]y Smith ALS to John Corlis; Providence, [Rhode Island], 1 page; Requests prices for black and white marble and Newark stone for fireplaces. Provides dimensions for the needed marble slabs.
  - 1800 April 25. [George Deneale?] Cy to [Henry] Lee; Alexandria, [Virginia], 2 pages; Notes alarm raised by Lee's Congressional resolution regarding the formation of rules and regulations for the District of Columbia. People fear for their liberties, "this is owing to a supposition that congress at present can have no knowledge of the people or their local situation and of course cannot have their Interests in view in assuming the Jurisdiction at this early period." Asks for advice about having to relinquish his position in Virginia government or national government.
  - 1800 May 8. John C[osens] Ogden ALS; New Castle, Delaware, 2 pages; Making arrangements for the return of the papers concerning the Congressional claim by his mother-in-law, Mary Clap Wooster, widow of Gen. David Wooster (1711-1777). "The happy hour appears to be approaching when in the change of men, and measures of a national concern, the patriots of 1776, and military men in the revolutionary war, will find patrons & benefactors, at least to pity, and to hear their just, modest & manly supplications with patience and decency."
  - 1801 August. [Elbridge Gerry] AL to [William?] Jenks; Cambridge, Massachusetts, 5 pages; Instructions written in the third person regarding education of "the children," commenting on philosophy of education, books and other materials, and curriculum. Believes the children's education "can only be promoted, by making it a pleasure." The "Globes, maps, & books" of the school need attention. Lists the books in use at the school. Provides instructions for the whitewashing of fences and painting of the barn and outhouses, including recipes for paints (white, yellow, and olive).
  - 1801 December 23. DS; Hatfield, [Massachusetts], 1 page; Pledge to pay for a school master, to teach two evenings per week during the months of January and February. Includes ten signatures.